Guide to the International Brotherhood of Teamsters Eastern Conference of Teamsters records 1954-2001 IBT0023
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
IBT Eastern Conference of Teamsters Records
1954-2001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America.
International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America
IBT0023
1 Linear Feet
This collection contains correspondence, meeting minutes, legal documents, financial records, programs, pamphlets, and reports. The material dates from 1954-2001. These are the records of the Eastern Conference of Teamsters, a regional governance body in the structure of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, meeting minutes, legal documents, financial records, programs, pamphlets, and reports. The material dates from 1954-2001. These are the records of the Eastern Conference of Teamsters, a regional governance body in the structure of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters.
Arrangement
Organized into 4 series: Administrative Files, Policy Committee Meeting and Agenda, Financial Records, and Pamphlets
Biographical / Historical
Within the International Brotherhood of Teamsters, between 1937 and 1995, members of the union met and exchanged ideas on a regional basis. These regional organizations were called Area Conferences. In the U.S. there were four area Area Conferences: the Western Conference of Teamsters formed in 1937, the Southern Conference of Teamsters formed in 1944, the Central States Conference of teamster formed in 1953, and the Eastern Conference of Teamsters also formed in 1953. Canadian Teamsters had their own Canadian Conference of Teamsters, known today as Teamsters Canada. Area Conferences met annually to discuss general issues facing the IBT and to hold discussion more directly relevant to IBT Trade Divisions: contract negotiations, organizing campaigns, workplace disputes, etc. For example, when the Central States Conference met, after the general sessions, delegates would meet based on the trades they represented: the brewery and soft drink delegates coming together, cannery delegates coming together, dairy delegates coming together, etc. In this way, the IBT was strengthened in terms of both national and regional coordination of efforts. The Area Conferences came under criticism during the General Presidency of Ron Carey. Making the argument that they were redundant and wasteful, Carey disbanded them in 1995.
Labor unions -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Conferences; Labor; Labor unions
- Administrative Files, 1954-1986; Series 1; 0.5 Linear Feet
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the administrative files of the Eastern Conference of Teamsters from 1954-1986 and includes correspondence, agendas, divisional reports, charters, bylaws, and other files pertaining to the everyday operation of the Eastern Conference.
  - Annual Report of the Chairman, 18 October 1954; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Report of the Chairman, 1956; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Report of the Chairman, 1958; Series 1 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Annual Report of the Chairman, 1962; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bylaws, 1958,1962,1966,1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Handbook - Building Construction, 1961; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - International Director's Report - 7th Area Conference, June 1964; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - International Director's Report - 13th Area Conference, August 1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Manual For Union Organizers, October 1970; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Manual For Union Organizers, 1974; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - A Study of Dairy Sales Drivers Contracts, 1958; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Policy Committee Meetings and Agenda, 1958-2001; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains material from the Building and Construction Conferences within the Eastern Conference of the International Brotherhood of Teamsters. The materials in this series range from 1958 to 2001.
  - Building and COnstruction Conference, 18 April 1958; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Building and COnstruction Conference - Trade Division Meeting, 24-28 June 1974; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Eastern Meeting Working Agenda, 25-27 March 2001; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Eastern Conference Agreements, 1964-1968; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - ICC Transfers Applications for Operating Authority, Ect., March - September 1960; Series 2 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Financial Records, 1954; Series 3; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains all financial materials related to the Eastern Conference of Teamsters, including summary of wages for the Brewing and Soft Drink Industry, and the Building and Construction Industry. The materials in this series are from 1954.
  - Eastern Conference of Teamsters Brewing and Soft Drink Industry Summary of Wages, 1954; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Eastern Conference of Teamsters Building and COnstruction Industry Summary of Wages, 1954; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Pamphets, Series 4; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains pamphlets related to the Eastern Conference of Teamsters. The materials in this series are from 1954.
  - 4 Pamphlets: "Shop Steward's Manual" "The Law and You" "Suggested Contract Clauses" "When You're 65", 1968; Series 4 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Testimonial Dinner - Fifty Years of Continuous Service, January 7, 1961; Series 4 (Box SHARED Box 31, Folder 5)
- Research Department Files
- Research Department Files, Series 5
  - National Over-the-Road Freight Study, Undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - National Over-the-Road and Local Cartage Freight Study, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - National Master and Eastern Conference Area Supplemental Agreements Freight Guide, 1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)